hello everyone welcome to the active
inference Institute uh this is cohort 8
and we are looking at chapter two of the
active influence textbook we're still in
the first half of the book so we're
looking at a lot more Theory a lot less
practice but it's with chapter 2 that we
suddenly find ourselves getting plunged
into a variety of terms many of which
will be familiar to folks who are
interested or already familiar with
probability Theory
statistics basian
Theory information Theory working
potentially with matrices for some of
our
examples um
and yeah statistics in general so a lot
of this sometimes comes off as
intimidating to those who don't
necessarily have a mathematical
background uh I do promise it's worth
bearing through it if only to become
more familiar with the terms and to try
and get what you can out of some of the
more sort
of somewhat more common sensical maybe
that's not quite the right word but
examples of you know if You observe
something jumping is it an apple or is
it a frog right it's it's like being
able to pH rephrase things in rather
simpler terms helps to clarify meanwhile
for those who are familiar with a lot of
these terms were also introduced to uh
kind of the framing for looking at
things like expectations surprise how do
we tie together biological inference
with basian Theory what is the
difference between surprisal versus
basian surprise and some of these kind
of key figures in the textbook really
help to paint more of a picture uh I say
tongue and cheek as we look at a picture
um in trying to understand something
like how an action perception Loop works
now we've already been through the
course of this chapter introduced the
idea of an agent uh on or or a
generative
model uh there there are arguments as to
whether the agent is its generative
model or perhaps it's just equipped with
a generative model in either case this
generative model is essentially
representative of whatever kind of
problem or task the the agent is trying
to solve or faces um and then we also
have the generative process which can uh
comes off as a synonym here for the
environment so we there's the notion of
a marov blanket which is also incredibly
Central to active inference and Daniel
and I were just chatting about it just
prior to this um this session and so we
we notice there's nothing here directly
connecting the agent and the environment
other than this y here this
observation that's what is emitted by
the the quote unquote true hidden state
of the environment denoted by X asterisk
here and then that's used to infer the
hidden state in the the mind so to speak
the generative model of the
agent um we notice we have Dash lines
denoting sort of the marov blankets and
I think the authors themselves note this
um the U for Action just as the agent
takes in the why the observations the
the agent emits an action um it it
shouldn't be too mixed up this U uh
later figures back in in a later figure
and and it's it might be a little
difficult to understand that it's it's
actually an active state it it might be
better represented here between the just
as y between them U should also be
between the model and the process um
those are the sensory why an active U
states that kind of Define like these
these boundaries and also nonetheless
are sort of the vi vicarious pipelines
or passageways almost between the Markov
blankets of the agent versus the
environment other ideas we're introduced
to are that are very important is that
the way that the agent models the true
state of the environment it's it's
always more or less attempting to
approximate something from the
environment that said there's no
necessity that this x is equivalent to
the true state in fact there's not even
a necessity that this x is structured
equivalent ly to the true State you know
if uh you know if if I'm hungry and I'm
tired uh there's no necessity that I
think that I'm hungry and I'm tired I
might be thinking in very different ways
about those things um
so that's just an attempt to give you a
quick view of sort of what active
inference is really looking at
ultimately we have a partially
observable environment meaning we can't
actually see the real environment we're
always kind of vicariously like trying
to interpret it and understand it
through our sensory observations
perception and through action we are
active in Furs we don't simply take in
passive observations we or rather we
don't passively take in observations we
emit actions as well uh that in fact
goes on to condition the environment
around us which then elicits new
observations so we can kind of see how
the the model and the process each have
their own kind of respective Logics
which can work incredibly similarly uh
but they also don't have to or at least
they don't have to be structured the
same um if I knock on wood because it
makes me feel better is it actually
doing anything other than kind of making
me feel better sometimes I do it anyway
because I know it makes me feel better
because I have that mental Association
it's that sort of sort of logic that I'm
I'm trying to get at and so that it's
just a reminder action as inference we
act it's part of the inferential process
right and then some other key ideas are
looking at like minimizing variational
free energy um this essentially what
we're trying to do or the claim of
active
inference as as well as potentially the
Basi and brain hypothesis and other
related areas but but this is of course
looking directly at the FP the free
energy principle um we're looking at
trying to uh minimize our uncertainty of
course uncertainty prediction error
variational free energy expected free
energy surprisal basy and surprise these
are all various terms that we find
through the book they all do have their
own nuances to them they come into play
at different times um but in some sense
they're very relatable uh conceptually
at least but for variational free energy
this is the this is kind of the the
trick and it's not just a trick it plays
out mathematically and we see we see it
with Jan's inequality but variational
free energy the whole reason why we're
doing this uh compute why if the goal is
to just minimize our surprise you know
so that we can better understand
everything why are we including this
variational free energy term why do we
have a variational free energy term why
do we have free energy principle at all
um the idea is that surprisal is
unfortunately very difficult to compute
um for those who have worked with let's
say like deep learning and neural
networks right if you have a fully
connected Network there's an immense
amount of information being passed uh
depending on how you set up your
parameters and what kind of state spaces
you're working with you quick run into
issues of intractability where it's
something just quite literally like does
not compute um similarly here uh with
variational free energy the idea is that
we get an approximation of surprisal uh
it it plays out really well because
through Jan's inequality uh which which
we'll get to later probably in a couple
weeks with chapter four I think is where
uh where it is uh what what it allows us
to do is say okay well we can't directly
compute surprisal but based upon
particular assumptions as well as as
well as mathematical like proofs and how
it plays out surprise uh can actually be
upper bounded by variational free energy
there's no necessity that variational
free energy equates to surprise but it
is a very fair approximation and we know
that surprise might not be equivalent
but we know that it won't be any higher
than
variational free energy with variational
free energy by doing things like mean
field approximation being able to sort
of marginalize out variables from joint
distributions and so on WE essentially
are kind of carving things up in a way
that is easier to work with them um it's
found through different neurobiological
studies and fact that we we do engage in
approximate methods uh it would be very
taxing on us
if not intractable it'd be incredibly
taxing on us to perfectly compute
everything at any given moment uh
including Trying to minimize our
uncertainty and that's not even getting
into the other sensory aspects such is
like you know just because I can see
everything in my field of vision it
doesn't mean that I'm actually
processing very intently every single
bit of what I'm taking in we're very
biased towards things that tend to be
interesting to us align with our goals
in terms of pragmatic value
or or things that interest us that we
might learn from in terms of epistemic
value so with free energy we we see that
there's this process of kind of engaging
in free energy minimization relative to
our engagement with the uh environment
all through reception changing your mind
to minimize the difference Oh I thought
it was 5:00 but I look at the time it's
actually 6:16 I'm going to change my
mind it is 616 or action to change the
world I am hungry I'm going to eat food
now I'm no longer hungry in this case
this is has to do with the idea of
interoception I'm reading my own signals
from my body in that in that instance
it's as if my own body is the
environment for me right uh there's a
nice neuroscientist uh Yori busak who
said that the the brain doesn't know I
think at least Elman Barrett said this
too you know it's a bunch of neurons
right so and many other things too but
but it's
conceptu very interesting so um I've
been going for some time expected free
energy we'll just touch on that real
quick um I used earlier this phrase uh
pragmatic value right food is in my
environment I'm hungry I expect to not
be hungry
so I will take an action that minimizes
expected free energy in order
to saap my hunger by eating the food
that is my action Information Gain I
already mentioned that earlier that's I
thought it was 5 o'l I check the time
turns out I have new information I
didn't really accomplish too much but I
did learn
something those are some kind of more
everyday ways of attempting to describe
how these Dynamics play out these kinds
of equations are very
important to be able to get some
intuitive grasp of especially if you're
still waiting your way through the
textbook um it's great part of the the
the strength of active inference that
I've always appreciated is being able to
apply these sort of more qualitative
terms to different aspects of active
inference such that you don't
necessarily have to know all of the
underlying maths in order to talk about
active inference or do research in
active inference or write about it um
you know you don't necessarily need to
know it in any kind of deep
sophisticated sophisticated way as long
as you're able to link the terms up
appropriately um never a bad idea to
work with a computational modeler or a a
statistician or otherwise to to Really
clarify your thoughts but
nonetheless um very Poss there have been
many interesting Papers written in
active inference on phenomenology
cognitive science uh social theory uh
imagining ways that we could apply
active inference to a variety of fields
mental health um so um there's plenty in
this chapter I believe it's the longest
chapter in the book um there's a lot we
could touch on
so um is anyone
interested in talking about any piece of
this or anything that stuck out or any
Curiosities questions that came up over
the course of reading
it yes Stephen please go
for I apologize if there's background
noise I just wanted to say that I in
going over the chapter and looking at
some YouTube videos to try to understand
it better I found um artam Ken's YouTube
on uh the cross
entropy um term or the reason why that
is used separating out that um the Q
value the the
uh I don't know all the terms but uh
where you don't have to do the complete
computations you just know what the
um Divergence is
um it was it was what what really
clicked for me was the
variational
um what's it called um V variational
free energy variational proba
um uh using the analogy
of image generation from Deep learning
um drawing
from the the probability configuration
the data structure of images that they
were trained on and in the in the brain
of course the data structure that were
trained on is the
world and and the Brain
learns the data structure just from
trial and error from experience so the
brain figures out the variational free
energy I mean it it it it it it um is
it's deriving or it it yeah learns the
variational free energy from you know
what is what are the probability data
structures of the world which is why the
more experience a person
has the better predictions one makes uh
the the the
more interaction with the actual World
instead of simulations of the world or
imaginations of the world uh the better
the predictions become I mean it just
this the explanation helped me
understand what why variational free
energy
is the the the right framing um you know
uh comparing it to the brain how it
grows and develops and what we're left
with um I
and I and I had a question I I wonder if
it's okay to ask um you can tell me if
this will be covered later but I've i' I
always want to try to see how this is
being
applied in the sense of the way the
nervous system is set up where there is
constant sensory input and motor
output but that motor output is both
sent to the affectors but also sent to
the internal
model and the internal model or
motor um a copy of the motor
command is sent to a what we're going to
call the internal model but the the
networks that will respond to whatever
the motor effectors are doing and it's
comparing are the predicted
sensory responses the same as the actual
sensory
responses right and when there's a
difference then the model is updated or
you know the neuron synaptic weights are
changed and I'm I'm
wondering how can I see
that
in this active inference model like in
the figure that you just
showed uh you know where there's the
internal model and then there's the
world and we're we're updating the model
it didn't look you know in my mind there
are parallel paths there's the motor
command and the internal copy it's
called the eer copy motor
command and the internal motor
command is creating it a it's
activating a internal model of the
sensory input that would be the result
of that motor
command which is then compared with the
actual sensory input of that motor
command and that's the way we're
continually
improving
the actual motor
commands so yeah so
there's I will
say you will definitely
get more out of this
textbook in terms
of what it is you're describing and what
you're interested in um I just want to
quickly find because there
many not trying to give anyone uh you
know Whiplash here but I'm just kind of
jumping around a little bit um so with
chapter I think it's at the end of
chapter
eight and I'll and I'll just hang on
this figure for a bit
um
yeah so a few different things um and
this is more like you know there will be
some loose ends that kind of open up
here but a few terms you might want to
look for in the
textbook um that's the fortunate thing
about this being freely you know uh
downloadable online and uh pulling up a
PDF and just hitting control F to just
kind of Zoom around through the textbook
uh a few phrases are
proprioception uh sensory
attenuation um this might relate as well
in terms of like trying to direct ly
model um some of the Dynamics you're
describing which are H uh this this
would be a what is at once a
hierarchical and mixed or hybrid model
um and it doesn't necessarily have to be
hybrid but all those things first
proprioception um is related to to kind
of like so so with inactive inference we
have what are called Observation
modalities it's a formal term certainly
not unique to active inference but it's
you
know my eyes allow me to to see and so I
have a visual observation modality uh
and so it's like I'm taking in visual
information so you can think of that as
a data stream and and I have the the
receptor or the sensory receptor for
accepting visual stimuli or observations
right um and then and then there's
exteroception
or exteroceptive observation modalities
which would kind of be describing things
that are coming from without these are
very cognitive kind of Neuroscience
related terms so um you know they're
kind of human centered or at least
organism centered but but Inception
would be signals coming from within
exteroceptive signals would be those
coming from without and then
proprioceptive would actually have to a
lot more to do with kind of movement uh
it could be you know in the sense of
like a reflex arc for example um so from
there sensory attenuation which is
always something interesting to wrap
one's head around um in active inference
it's it comes off as a little
counterintuitive but actually once I
understood it it was one of the most
fascinating Concepts they have and it
makes sense from within the framework
which is much of active inference you
know given the basian lens we're always
bringing some kind of Prior or what you
expect
to the situation what you that that
includes prior on uh hidden States uh
like what you infer to be going on uh
but then there's also priors about
observations right and so whenever
you're describing this kind of aspect of
having a model up for the sensory
stimuli itself itself for the data
stream where it's you know it's it has
to figure out what the observations
themselves mean um you could view that
as and and then and then once it kind of
figures out what they mean it it sends
that further to another part of say a
model to engage in further or deeper
inference
here this hybrid model is kind of saying
at this very fast time scale I'm taking
in these y observations rather rather
quickly right at each step of this
slower model up
here a single you know this T minus one
or to minus one so at one time Step at
the higher level we actually have three
time steps at the lower so the idea is
that at different levels you can have
different time scales of the inference
process but all this is to say and I'll
try and because I hope I I prefer to
clarify more than I make ambiguous uh
you know an answer to your question but
um it would be something like you could
model what does the incoming data mean
and then from there based on what you
think it means how does that fit into
another inference process for making
higher order decisions or making higher
order inferences and given the whole
partial observable Paradigm uh it is I
mean yeah there's there's no necessity
that the data you receive is one to one
with the Real Environment um I mean this
account given the you know the the the
more human Centric or organism Centric
robotic Centric aspects of active
inference it's like what happens
whenever you have a bad sensory receptor
right like you still have to kind of
figure out what an observation is or
means and so you could imagine like in a
in a in a more realistic sense I mean
this could be an incredibly long complex
like
deep um uh model here where so many
different inference processes are
happening in different time scills you
know layering things
up then the only thing is why do any
kind of modeling if in reality
everything is that complicated or at
least we think it is well with active
inference as well as any other form of
machine learning or deep learning we're
ultimately just trying to come up with a
good model that generally
approximates uh the the phenomena of
Interest or at least can can predict on
it um and it needs to be not too complex
otherwise it'll
overfit uh and and also be
computationally inefficient you know
like me describing like earlier like you
know if I took in every single bit of
information and computed every single
bit of information every bit of
surprisal that there could be I mean I'm
either going to hit intractability or
massive exhaustion in a certain way um
and and yet accuracy so I want it to be
good um
and I guess referring to where you you
started with variational free energy
that that's right I mean it would be to
to approximate um so so to to create a
model itself isn't just to try and be
hyper
accurate that's not just because of
intractability or difficulty it's also
because it might not be a good idea to
do that as soon as there's some kind of
paradigm shift in the environment right
right so like if I'm in my home versus
in a car I will act very differently
right um if I am overfit or I do overfit
my generative model to being
indoors then as soon as you put me in a
driver's seat I will have no idea what
to do everything will be very surprising
any kind of strategy I would have will
be biased towards something I would do
indoors
it would be problematic so having
approximation and generalizability goes
beyond just you know uh any kind of
Cheap Trick uh uh not that anyone has
said that but it just like just it's
it's not so simple it's it actually
helps for adaptation right so yeah if I
could that was wonderful the the nervous
system of course is composed of 10 to
the 10th
individual predictor you know models you
know neurons and it's organized
to
selectively suppress everything but what
is needed at the
moment and I I see what you what you've
showing is kind of giving an example of
that
it uh on on so many different levels
from The Reflex level to the cognitive
no I want to be doing this now and say
centering attention on one
particular
model yeah no that's great I'm glad this
was helpful and it's you know so this
model here is just jumping to chapter
eight right so this is this is Way
Beyond where anyone you know who has
just started the textbook and they're
only at chapter two now like that they
wouldn't even have to consider any of
these pieces of architecture yet other
than
a couple things like we saw the Y
earlier your observations and then X the
hidden States but all of this about G
about F functions about you know Adas
and so on a
matrices that hasn't quite figured yet
we do have G expected free energy so
it's kind of like this is you know it is
a textbook so you can certainly like
kind of build your way up to this and
frankly I think this would be one of the
most
complex models that's shown throughout
the textbook
um yeah by the time we get to chapter
nine it actually reverts to well not
reverse but this is more about
modelbased data analysis so this is more
about kind of taking what we've learned
adding on a few other forms of analysis
for kind of like understanding our
models or building or iterating
overbuilding models and and even fitting
models uh and then using them for uh you
you know by fitting them we can get into
kind of empirical data analysis as well
as like um you know if you're working
with with groups of of individuals that
you're analyzing right then you can you
know look at summary statistics or or
other kinds of analyses per group um but
yeah it's yeah it's really just getting
that initial intuitive grasp figure 9.1
has always been kind of fun um you know
it's this
is uh a PDP model which is just a
discrete State space model which you
know you could you it's not
dramatically there's certain kinds of
conceptual overlaps this could happen
with like a hot field Network or
something along those lines where it's
like you know you could have States just
being a neurons charge being positive or
or negative or or something is
excitatory or or inhibitory or otherwise
kind of like Reet valued um but anyway
the the bigger point of this figure 9.1
as we zoom out is that we're just being
aware like we have our own we the
experimenters have our own idea of what
the model is and what it should be so
it's rather meta but I've kind of
appreciated the sort of
self-awareness that uh that active
inference practices because at the end
of the day we are making a lot of
decisions anyone working with with neur
neuroimaging data or otherwise is making
a lot of decisions whenever they start
modeling and there are things that you
know will be these kind of blaring never
leave the back of your mind like sort of
issues with modeling that are like oh I
I need to include that but I have no
idea how and I can't even you know so so
we have to make certain kinds of like
hard decisions sometimes when it comes
to modeling and to bring it back back um
that would be sort of the case for
organisms too right like like all this
computational modeling we're doing based
on textbooks like this and reinforcement
learning and so on and apologies if I'm
if I'm getting too abstract or
philosophical but it's like similarly
you could think of the brain as like
well you know if I start a new job uh
you know place of employment and I'm
trying to figure out like you know how
does this work what are my social
dynamics with my co-workers you know
what is kind of our our degree of
professionalism and and um you know how
do we how do we sort out doing meetings
and who is the best person to talk to
about this topic and all kinds of things
I'm going to have to start kind of at
least implicitly modeling how this goes
because I'm going to presumably be
engaging with my job like you know X
number of hours per week or you know
scheduled meetings or otherwise um so so
any any scenario would come to whether
it be trying to model you know myself
properly engaging in my position of
employment or it' be us trying to model
how a mouse in a teammate's behavioral
task you know functions and how it is
that they infer where the reward is on
the left side or the right side of the
teamas and what are the steps that they
take to get there and how do they decide
that or determine that based on their uh
sensory observation
I mean it's it's just a a lot of
modeling to
do and and it's almost always
approximate life moves
quickly
um I mentioned sensory attenuation too
earlier that's kind of
a fun one but I don't want to introduce
too much too
quickly let's see if this is a good
place to pick up on that the
implications that we need to be able to
attend away from proprioceptive data by
turning down their gain this gain is
given by the Precision or inverse
variance with which these data are
predicted to attenuate this we need
descending motor tracks to predict not
just the data but the Precision of or
confidence placed in those data
decreasing this prision to initiate
movement while this for some will come
off as very complex passage and it it
really is but but this is chapter 5 so
there's a good deal that you'll have
learned by the time you reach this area
sensory attenuation is interesting in
part because like as a as sort of a
learning hortic for active inference I
think because it what it what it
revolves around is this sort of basian
Paradigm that is we bring our own
beliefs to the situation and a lot of
things have to do with
expectations right so there's a kind of
strange philosophical conundrum that can
come up when considering that well if
you expect that right now you are
sitting in place you might have a goal
to you know I might have a goal to stand
up but currently I expect myself to be
sitting you that's that's what I'm
observing right now I notice I'm still
sitting down so how if it's the case
that we engage in like basy and
inference then how is it that I ever get
up from the shair at all if my priors or
expectations are always
reinforcing um you know what I'm doing
or what I expect and that's influencing
my action so sensory attenuation is the
sense that in everyday terms very
everyday terms because I notice the time
and I'm kind of droning a little bit
about this but the idea would be that
it's almost as if your sensory receptors
have to not pause but heavily turn down
their own G game like in order to
actually finally get up out of the chair
I have to it's almost as if I'm
forgetting that I'm in the chair I I
need to move in order to make something
happen and so it's a it's a rather
interesting framing for looking at how
how we actually accomplish goals while
reconciling this idea of you know the
fact that we're we're always inferring
um give me just one second because I
realized the chat's been very
um let see there was a question about
this
is backtracking but let's uh because
it'd be good to get ourselves reentered
in chapter
two been taking us on a journey um so
expected free
energy we'll go to that equation
I will look a little bit more at some of
these
terms so like
here there's a question about pragmatic
value so what is this the
expectation of the natural log of the
conditional probability
distribution y with a Tilda meaning it's
a sequence or it can be a sequence uh
one plus elements in the sequence
conditioned on
C so I don't know if it was nice of the
authors or not to so quickly introduce
us to G whenever we're still missing
some things like what is c um but that's
okay so C uh
here I mentioned earlier the the pi the
pomdp model that we were looking at
which is for discrete State spaces I was
zooming in on those figures and chapters
8 and chapter n um to C is a term
denoting your priors over
observations so this is kind of like
saying if we just reduce to this it's
kind of like what is the
probability of this sequence of
observations conditioned
on the observations I expect and so
pragmatic value is the idea is very much
related or almost the way it's used is
almost identical to the idea of reward
seeking has so so it's not about seeking
out
information for its own sake to change
your mind it's about directly going to
an award uh reward if I expect to not be
hungry then if I'm observing that I'm in
fact not hungry or I'm I'm you know then
then this probability is going to be
very high right like my model is
accurate in terms of achieving pragmatic
value on the hunger end of things
okay so uh from from the text that said
the SE is the preferences so basically
this probability is the probability that
you see the observations that you would
want to see right because it means you
have the string of
observations in in the world that is
your preferences which means you get the
probab means you get the observations
that you want to see and it's the
probability of that couple questions
though uh why the logorithm and also um
it it has to do with the probability
that you see what you want to see but it
doesn't say anything about how much you
want to see what you want to see
typically pragmatic value isn't about
just How likely you are to get what you
want but how much you actually want what
you
want yeah just a few a few quick answers
there
the shape of C is a distribution over
the observations it does exactly tell
you how much you prefer different
observations like you could have um 131
or
121 that's a sharper preference in the
second case why is it a log um there are
several convenient properties of logs
for probability which is why likelihood
distributions are often framed in terms
of log likelihoods for example yeah EX
exactly like those are the different
sharpness but log um allow properties
like log of a b is log of a plus log of
B so if you have two independent
probabilities you can separate them so
those are basic log properties and also
for computation when you're dealing with
low probabilities it's easier to store a
negative log as a large number like 1
billion rather than a tiny number and it
has properties that are important for
statistics mapping between the zero to
one interval so there's a ton of reasons
why logs are used in general in
statistics all of those are in play and
then the preferences are a distribution
over observations and they can express
the strength and the directions of
preferences yeah thanks Dan oh let's uh
have another
quick look at
that exactly so it's kind of like just
as Daniel mentioned like if if C is sort
of a distribution over all of your
preferred or or expected observations
and then you get uh a sequence of
observations and you could view this you
know in the PDP in the discrete State
space setting you could view this as
like oh um you know there's there are
three different possible
observations uh I
prefer the first one with full
probability 1.0 the other two is zero
which means I completely do not want
observation index two or three I just
want the first possibility out of the
three um so um like uh I'm I'm I'm
hungry I'm completely famished or I am
fully sated I prefer being fully sated
right so the sequence of observations
could be you know an observation of
being fully stated not the others and
then once again being fully stated not
the others but then for maybe a third
time step now I'm hungry right so there
would be you know of course I'm just
kind of making this up as we go but you
know this so that would mean this
probability would not be exactly one uh
if I were sated for all three of those
time steps then it would be one right it
be that be exactly what I expect and
then it's called expected free energy
and that's some folks are like well why
do we have a variational and then we
have an expected the and why is it
called expected and so with expected
free energy this is free energy of the
future so to speak and it does kind of
have its own um set of equations to it
but we'll notice that it's being scored
for each action or policy that could be
taken so a policy would be a whole
sequence of actions into the future and
so whereas f is pretty let's say
reactive in a
sense in that it takes
in an observation Computing free energy
to compute your posterior overstates
meaning I took in this observation what
is the free energy that helps me Reach
the the sort of optimal approximate
posterior Over States if my stomach
growls best inference would be I'm
hungry
probably expected free energy will be oh
there's a series of things I could do in
the sense of actions and sequences of
actions I could take so
given I could take an action associated
with a sequence like I could get up and
go to the store to get food um by the
end of that sequence at least uh
hopefully at some point involves me
eating the food and no longer being
hungry right so to think about it
computationally simply that g is just
scoring each of the kind of actions or
policy sequences of actions
that you could take we want to minimize
G as our optimization function these two
terms is kind of all you need um to look
at these others two but but for now
we'll just focus on this
um this is kind of like saying by doing
a set of
actions you know what will be its
pragmatic value how closely does it
match my expected observations my
preferences what I want
which from a you know a more General
perspective C could very be well be what
defines your constraints for maintaining
homeostasis so it so C could also be oh
my blood oxygen level is you know at a
proper balance or or uh hunger I I keep
going to that one that's a pretty good
example of achieving homeostasis to make
sure your uh caloric balances in
place and then Information Gain is kind
of like it's it's interesting because as
opposed to variational free energy where
K Divergence is you know it's it's kind
of we want to minimize it here we're
actually wanting to to maximize it
because both of these terms are negative
right if we want to minimize G then we
actually want to maximize Information
Gain and pragmatic value so with
Information Gain you can look at this as
what is what do I believe or what will I
believe given the observations I think
I'll come across when engaging this set
of actions
versus what do I believe is usually the
case when I do that set of actions so
really the only when when looking at the
taale Divergence here the only thing
that separates these and makes it a you
know a non-zero Divergence by not
equating the same two things or or or
putting JS opposing the same two things
is is the why so so we're looking at a
kind of scenario where it's like I'm
seeking out doing things that bring
about observations that actually change
my mind and ultimately because of the
particular terms here it's kind of like
saying I want to find I want to do
things that change my mind about the
association between what I think is
going on and my actions and the the more
intuitive way of saying that is simply
I'm going to do things that get help me
get a better
understanding between how I think the
world Works based on what I do right so
imagine someone who opens up a textbook
to learn something right and then you
you could start learning about you know
oh I could apply active inference or I
could think about active there are all
kinds of ways that one could attempt to
use active inference whether it be for
you know brain computer interfaces or it
be used for
you know uh agent-based modeling in the
social sciences looking at you know
social media interactivity but you know
patterns in in networks um looking at
neuronal
Dynamics so so it's that both of these
are sort of like directives or
incentives that we have and then sort of
the classic bit with active inference
that's repeatedly stated in a lot of the
literature when comparing it to
reinforcement learning is that it's
these terms that are directly implicated
whenever people consider this sort of
explore
exploit uh
tradeoff so this this is a point I've
made personally I uh you know I did a
workshop at at upen at
a conference last summer and and you
know it was interesting to a lot of
people who weren't familiar with AC of
inference yet but did reinforcement
learning because when with reinforcement
learning obviously not always the case
but there are at least times where
people resort to defining some kind of
term for what what what is e exploratory
Behavior you know which is sometimes
it's as simple as like a Epsilon greedy
meaning uh you essentially saying like
oh the agent should always seek the
reward uh
point you know nine times out of 10 and
then point one like or 10% of the time
just do something random and then that
way you can avoid getting stuck in a
local Minima um but here we notice like
oh as long as you have the
equation for
G then exploitation and exploration are
both scored on their own individually
there's no hard coded 10% of the time
you do something random right so
if expected free energy computation
holds and we find that at a variety of
levels of you know life whether it be
neuronally
or for an entire
person or potentially even an entire
group of people depending on what level
of the nestedness of of markup blankets
you're looking I mean this is a way of
saying oh we don't need to hardcode a
particular value to say when you should
do something random in fact this isn't
even random right because you're
actually making direct references to
particular sequences of observation you
expect or States you expect or actions
you take so that's sort of the that's a
this is kind of a a major strength of
active inference and for myself is
someone who who's done a lot of kind of
reinforcement related work in the past
this is this is this was one piece of
kind of why I headed in this direction
because I just it seems so arbitrary to
do Epsilon greedy type stuff
um so is there any
anything in the few minutes we have left
any final thoughts any final questions
someone wants to pick up on
reminder to everyone that we have
a textbook
Koda this was a nice video that Daniel
and Ali did some time ago they they did
a sequence of book streams where they
did rather uh much more in depth sort of
overviews of each chapter sorry about
that and uh and it's kind of a nice way
within less than 30
minutes to go even deeper than I did
during the course of this particular
session so with a lot of highlights on
particular things that are worth putting
your attention
towards uh if you if you want to get the
most out of each chapter
and then for the sake of this cohort
since we are out of time uh so chapter
three will be next that'll instead be
the high road rather than the low road
to active inference so here we started
with uh you know we started in chapter
two with with Basi and
mechanics took that route and
then chapter 3 will be about starting
with the high road starting from the
free energy principle starting with
Notions of
self-organization surprise minimization
see much more detail on marov blankets
the idea of self- evidencing including
that trick about the sensory attenuation
I mentioned
earlier um predictive
processing so we'll we'll reach there
and then chapter after that chapter 4
we'll start to bring it back together
chapter
significantly more about message passing
looking at actual like microc cortical
circuits uh in terms of like neuronal
message passing uh in cortical layers um
so for anyone interested in
neurobiology um that's a particularly
fascinating one um I always have a good
time with it personally so um all right
everyone um thanks so much
there thanks Andrew by everyone